in the the waiting room to join on in.
In the meantime, good morning everybody.
Uh it looks like our recording has
started. Um and uh while everybody is
still coming on in through the um from
the waiting room and joining on in. Uh
my name is Dominic Zarlo with the New
Mexico Department of Health and we are
here today to assist the board uh with
um the logistics of this meeting. Um,
and so with that, just as a reminder to
everybody, um, because we are recording
this meeting and it is a public meeting,
um, please remember to keep your
language to be appropriate for being
posted online, um, because we do post
these onto our website. So, at this
point, I'll turn the meeting on over to
uh, Ian Dunn, who is the chair for the
medical psilocybin advisory board. Ian,
the meeting is yours.
>> Good morning, everyone. My name is Ian
Dunn. Uh, as the chair of the medical
psilocybin advisory board, I call this
meeting to order at 9:02 a.m. Mountain
Daylight Time. Um, before we dive into
the text and introductions of today's
meeting, I wanted to outline two
operational guardrails for today's
session just to ensure equity and proper
proper time management and respect for
everyone's schedule. So, first regarding
public comment, our standard operating
procedure is to keep public comment
separate from active board
participation. During our last session,
a member of the Public Lake was
inadvertently called on. Um during our
working discussion, today we are
returning strictly to our standard
format where public comment will occur
exclusively during its designated slot
at the end of the meeting. Secondly,
regarding time management, um we will
restrict we will adhere strictly to our
scheduled hours today. We did have some
board members that were unable to make
it to the final vote of the day. So we
just want to protect everyone's external
commitments and uh we will not call or
conduct any formal votes after our
scheduled uh adjournment time. So I will
now turn over to uh the department to
call roll to introduce the rest of the
board members
>> or Chris you had a question.
>> Yeah thank you Ian. I was wondering if
we could also during roll call um talk
about the appointed positions that
everybody was designated for
just for public awareness and so we can
clarify that for for everybody on the
board too.
>> Yes. If you would like you may share
your um what you were appointed for as
well as any other information you think
the public would um like to know about
you.
Well, can we have the other can we have
the board members?
But I don't think that's ever been
publicly acknowledged what roles
everybody was appointed for.
>> Sure. I'm going to once again turn it
over to the individual board members and
say if you would like to share um you
may otherwise I'm not going to say you
are required to but again we will turn
over to introductions
>> if it's okay with you uh Ian uh this is
Dominic and with Chris that uh I'm have
no problem with going ahead and [snorts]
um going through that part as we go
through the roll call we can uh outline
that aspect effect of it if that's fine
with you.
>> That's fine with me.
>> Okay. All right. Um so with that in
mind, we'll go ahead and start. Um and
so uh and I'm just going to go down the
list um that we have here. So uh Brenda
Burgard, who is the behavioral health,
uh appointee.
>> Uh hello everyone. I am Brenda Bergard.
I am a licensed LPCC counselor, art
therapist,
and um I'm also the president of the
DRIM um
for uh psychedelics in New Mexico. Um I
have a private practice here in
Albuquerque and um I chair the education
and training here for the Department of
Health.
>> Thank you, Brenda. Um Chris Pesky who is
the veteran appointee.
>> Good morning everyone. Uh you all know
who I am. Thank you. Happy to be here.
>> Dan Jennings who is an atlarge appointee
and also an advocate.
>> Thanks Dan Jennings. I'm the uh chair of
the research and continuous improvement
committee, vice chair of the board, and
also a city councelor here in Hagerman,
New Mexico, and director of 100% Chavis
County Initiative.
>> Thank you, Dan. And Desba, who is the
tribal member appointee.
>> Hi, Yata. Desba.
Uh and then Ian Dunn uh who is the um
advocate appointee.
>> Good morning everyone. My name is Ian
Dunn. Happy to be here and happy to help
the community.
>> And Larry Leman who uh is uh with UNM as
well and uh is an atlarge appointee.
>> Hi everybody. Good to see everybody
today. I am um professor of family
medicine, addiction medicine, master of
public health um and a psilocybin
researcher. Thank you.
>> And uh Ryan Kenan who is uh the uh
designate for the HCA appointee.
>> Apologize all for that. Uh my name is
Kenan Ryan. I am our acting chief
medical officer for New Mexico Medicaid.
I am covering for Dr. Alana Dances who
was our uh Medicaid director and former
primary care provider um out of
Albuquerque, New Mexico.
>> And my apology tenan for switching your
names around.
>> Uh you know, my life just exists. It's
kind of a Schroinger box situation. I
just have two first names. Um whichever
one happens at that time.
>> I appreciate your grace on that. Thank
you. Uh and those are the board members
who are present. Did I miss anybody? I
believe I have everyone.
>> I believe that was everyone. Uhuh. So, I
will go ahead and turn it over to the
department for what you guys wanted to
present.
>> Uh um before we do that, Ian, just to
introduce who um the um introduce the
the department members who are here
today. And I'm just going to go down the
list. It's in no particular order. Um
myself, Dominic Zerlo. I'm the director
for the center for medical cannabis and
psilocybin. We have Kathy Ajeri who is
our project manager related with IT and
other items similar. Kathy Fryag one of
our health educators, Raymond Gyos,
one of our uh analysts, Jorge Gonzalez
who is our sil medical psilocybin
program manager. Brenda Martinez who is
our center deputy director, Jonathan
Musher who is our management analyst and
uh actually helps to set up all of these
meetings and could not do what we do
without any of these folks but
especially Jonathan from uh the
logistics side. Rosalie Nava who is our
health education program manager, Leslie
Peterson who is our compliance officer,
Cyrus Routman who is our environmental
scientist um and we have Dr. Robert
Truckner who is our medical director and
then we have a new individual joining us
today. Uh we just started yesterday with
an intern. His name is Vicente Royal and
uh he is going to be interning with us
through the summer to learn about
psilocybin and to help us with some of
the projects related to this. And so
thank you everybody and welcome to the
team Vicente.
>> Um excuse me Demick I'm not sure if you
introduced Raymond.
>> Yes I did. Uh, one of our Raymond, one
of our analysts. Yes, thank you, Jorge,
though, for checking because that was my
next question. Did I catch everybody?
Sometimes it's a little difficult to see
on the long list of people that we have
to make sure I have everybody. Did I
miss anybody from our team?
Okay. And so just to let everybody know
um the next item and it is actually the
document that we had sent out on
Tuesday. Um and uh let me just pull that
up on the screen. So please give me just
a moment to switch files.
And just for a note, um anybody who
signed up after Tuesday, I just sent
that out to you guys just now. So,
thank you, John.
Okay. And so, here is uh the the rules.
And again, as I had stated last week or
two weeks ago, um the these are still
being drafted. We are still working
through them. You will see that some of
the different sections are now put more
into the regulatory format. Some of the
other sections are not yet into that
regulatory language format, but we are
continuing and thank you to everybody
who has been providing comments. We have
been getting comments. We are working
through them um and uh to see about
either addressing them, whether it's
adding some in. There have been quite a
few that have been added. Um, we've had
some comments for example with regard to
um, you know, uh, with some of the
certifications like BLS or CPR and we've
made some adjustments on that. For
example, um, it's been raised by a
couple of people that if someone also
has an EMT license, for example, would
we need to have them go through CPR
classes again? And we've added that on
in. So, you will see some of those kinds
of changes that are added on into here.
There are some others that have been
suggested um since we sent this out on
Tuesday that we may be adding on in and
we're awaiting some language and some
other information. For example, there's
been um some requests with adding some
additional cultural considerations uh as
far as for training or with adding uh
continuity of care plans um and some
other similar items. And so uh again we
are going through those kinds of
comments and everything on that. And
then I would like um before I start
diving into the document itself I would
like to apologize because it was me who
actually called on other individuals
outside the board. And uh part of that
was I've gotten so used to us working in
the various committees and having that
uh having that feedback automatically
and at that point in time that that was
me who had done that and my apologies to
the board because I just my brain was
working from that standpoint of yes
we're looking at feedback and wanting to
get feedback and so my apologies with to
the board and to everybody present
because that was my error. um but it was
done out of a place of trying to be as
transparent and trying to have those uh
conversations as we continue. So what I
do want to make sure that everybody does
know is that we are continuing to have
those conversations. Uh I think for
example the vast majority of this last
two weeks since the previous meeting has
been almost all having conversations
about how can we help and adjust the
rules? How can we have conversations to
be able to make this the best set of
rules and the program possible? So, I
just wanted to go ahead and start with
that. Now, in the interest of time to
make sure that we are able to get
through everything today, I'm not
necessarily going to read through every
single piece and bit of the the
document, but I will put the major
portions there. So for example the very
top of the document you can see it has
some of the items that are just required
within regulations about authority
duration effectiven effective date those
sort of things I'm not going to put
those items up but I will start with the
next set or with the first section
so that is now in the chat. Um and so
this portion is uh is with regard to the
application requirements for the
educational programs. Um and in in
essence what it includes Oh, I'm sorry.
Uh I didn't see Chris. Uh you have your
hand up.
>> I'm sorry. I guess I'm confused. I
thought on the agenda it said we were
going to talk about the three items that
we didn't discuss last week. But we're
going to do that as we go through the
document. Um my understanding was they
were put on the agenda to make sure that
we did discuss them as we went through
the document.
>> Uh well,
>> if you would like, we can go directly to
those. I don't have any issue with that.
>> I don't know. I'm just I'm I'm confused
because I I thought that was what was on
the agenda. So, uh are we shifting from
that, Ian? Is this a department meeting
or is this an advisory board meeting?
>> So the reason he was going to go through
the rest was not because it had
substantial changes but because the
changes were just to basically translate
from regular speak to regulatory
language. Um it wasn't in an attempt to
change anything. It was just as an
attempt to inform.
But we can just focus on the things that
were adjusted and that we need to
resolve. I think they were just trying
to go through the entire document to
create a flow. That way we're all
reminded of what is included and that
kind of thing.
>> So are we redising these items or are
they up for debate and vote or are we
just going through them forformational
purposes?
forformational purposes.
And and just to be clear, it would it's
up to the board. If you would prefer for
me to just go to those specific items,
uh I can most certainly do that.
>> I'll go ahead and um
defer to the board. Would you guys like
to review the updates that they had made
um to make it regulatory language or
would you just like to review the three
items on their own?
Larry,
>> sorry you thought Desbo was first. I
didn't see.
>> Hi. Um yeah, it's okay. Um, I just
wanted to just uh I will say I'll
propose that we do go just quickly
through those. Um, just you know if
we're taking an anatomy class, we want
to understand the whole body and where
we're at as opposed to just kind of
going in and operating on the appendix
type of situation. Um, so if anyone else
has a disagreement with that, then
that's fine.
>> Thank you, Larry.
>> Um, I I agree with Desba, but but I
actually think the whole thing is sort
of up for discussion. And I mean, you
can't sort of say one part of a document
is not because they actually affect each
other. So I I think those three are are
core core areas of controversy. But I
think if people have a problem with
other things, it's still game to mention
that,
>> right? And what I meant by those are
areas is those are the three that we
need to complete by the end of the
meeting. Um and then of course if
discussion naturally comes up as we're
going through theformational portion um
people can contest that but for the
purposes of just what we need to resolve
today it's those three issues. Um but I
agree with you and Desba that we should
know what beasts we're getting into.
Dan,
>> I am fine with going through the whole
document, but if we don't get to those
three, then we have done a disservice.
So, I want to make sure that we have
time to dig into those three and really
have good discussion on those specific
things.
>> Perfect. And then, Dominic, do you think
we can get through this fast enough to
still resolve the three issues?
>> I believe we can. And as I said, I'm not
going to be reading through each of the
sections. It's more to just ensure that
there aren't any other questions for
topics that may have been missed. Um,
and that's was just the original idea,
but that we were going to ensure that we
focus on those three areas as we
approach as we get to those. But again,
I'm it is up to the board.
I think we have pretty broad consensus
that we'd rather just hear the whole
piece. So, um, if you could just
continue with that. Thank you.
>> Okay.
>> Thank you everybody. Um, and so this
first section, it's just really the
application requirements for the
psilocybin educational programs. Um,
though the information in there has not
changed with regard to it. Um the one
thing that we did adjust um was to put
in uh for the documentation
demonstrating that they have two faculty
members who hold practitioner and
facilitator certificates is to extend
that out to June 30th because some of
the comments we got was December 31st
would be a little too short. So we did
extend that on out. Um and that's really
the only real change within this
section. Any questions?
Okay. Um the next part was again the um
required reporting and curriculum
approval. Um and then there is a section
about if a program wanted to relinquish
their certification
uh as a program and I'm putting that
into the chat now. Um, and so again,
this part didn't there were no actual
changes within here, any substantive
changes. Um, just really clarifying it,
[snorts] rearranging it a little bit and
adding it on in. And also to ensure and
clarify that yes, programs do have the
ability to um, relinquish their
certification if they wish.
>> Any questions on here? This this just is
really about what they the programs
would be required to submit updates to
their curriculum changes in faculty
locations um and that the approval
process uh is that they have to submit
it through the s the electronic system
to the department um with all of the
requirements previous listed previously
listed.
Okay.
Um and then um the evaluation and
assessment by the department and you
will notice that you know since last
time we have combined uh some of the
different aspects of this. So for
example um all of the um the assessment
actually it is because it's all similar
for all the different types of
certifications we're looking at for this
with locations. So it does show um the
educational programs, healing centers
and other locations and how those will
be evaluated and assessed. Um and so
going through that we have the ability
to um you know to do site on-site
inspections. We heard very clearly from
the last meeting and since to ensure
that we did have and it was simply an
oversight, but to ensure that only if it
was um if there were for example
practicums occurring or patient
treatment that it would happen at that
time only with written consent from the
patients. Um so that we ensure that we
are um
valuing and being respective of the
treatment process. Any
questions on this?
>> Brenda,
>> um what occurred to me was uh would
there be any training
for inhome um for example uh a death
doula? Uh, and uh could could that be
something that could be there where a
student would be in home with a death
doula or a death doula is the student or
does this have to be at a certified
um, you know, clinic?
>> Great question, Brenda. And please
forgive me if I'm misinterpreting your
question. Um, but I think what you're
getting at is for the practicum, could
the the practicum student be doing this
also at in a home setting? Um, for
example, along with the death doula or
other appropriate provider and would
that count as part of that? And the
answer to that is yes.
>> Am I understanding that correctly?
>> Yes. Thank you.
>> Yes. And that and where that that's why
we actually have the other approved
locations phrase because it's not just
necessarily healing centers and we do
have that as part of with the practicum.
You'll see that that it [snorts] has to
just be at a practicum or at a healing
center or other approved locations in
order to cover exactly that kind of
situation. It also would help, for
example, if in a um a more rural area
where there may be a lack of
practitioners where a a location can be
approved temporarily, for example, a
community center or a local nonprofit
who is offering their space to be able
to have uh people go through their
treatment through their journeys
especially in those spaces and this
would allow for the department to be
able to approve those and those also
serve as practicum sites.
>> Okay. So um uh would that be you know uh
hopefully that won't wouldn't be a long
process like if it was some in someone's
home for instance or
>> Okay. So we we've gotten very good um
over the years with how we are able to
do those kinds of compliance or those
sort of certification visits and they're
usually very quick and [snorts] we of
course would uh within our own internal
best practices or policies if for
example somebody is um you know with end
of life for example and this is a
time-sensitive situation we have uh and
we do this for example with regard to
cannabis where those applications for
example will take priority.
>> Okay, thank you.
>> Yeah, great question. Thank you.
>> Any other questions on that evaluation
and assessment portion?
>> Okay, the next portion is on the third
party evaluators. Um and uh we haven't
very changed very much with regard to
this section either. We did make some
clarifications in the language. Um with
that, um we have had several
conversations with different um uh
educational programs or potential
educational programs discussing what
exactly a um a third-party evaluation is
and talking about how that actually does
fit within the standards for curriculum
development and educational programs.
And we recognize that that may not have
been the case in many other areas within
the psychedelic education community. But
one of the things that we are trying to
do as a part of this process is to
elevate it to really those best
practices with regard to education
overall. And so this is something that
we are leaving in. We did explore the
ideas as were brought up in the last
meeting about CMEs and we did look at
that and understanding that if there
were also full evaluations that would
occur of the curriculum itself and as we
looked into the different CME programs
and CEU programs and had discussions
with several people who actually offer
them and who actually uh help to um I'm
not sure award is the right uh the right
term but who offer them uh to programs
to be able to offer CMEs for it is those
evaluations just were not happening.
While there are evaluations, for
example, uh pre and post evaluations of
the students and did they learn
information, they're not actually
evaluations of the curricula. So, we are
still looking into that aspect to see if
that portion if there is a potential
alternative path. But at this point, it
really is relying upon having that
third-party evaluator. And I do know
that there are some concerns as far as
cost with regard to that. Evaluation of
programs always does come with a cost.
We are trying to make sure that this is
done in a way that's going to be um as
cost-effective as possible. And that's a
part of why it's not a department
determined um third-party evaluators,
but why the criteria for what that
evaluation has to be is included in here
so that it is following those kinds of
best practices with curriculum
evaluation and also ensuring that things
remain confidential.
Um but we are still continuing to
explore those areas um and to see on
those and just as a reminder as was
mentioned in the beginning of the board
meeting um at this time I can only take
comments or questions from board
members.
So uh any questions from the board
regarding this or comments?
Okay, thank you everyone. Um and then
the next set are um the requirements for
certifying clinicians, practitioners,
and facilitators.
And I'll have that here in just a moment
into the chat.
Okay. Uh and so um this has changed a
little bit. The overall topics have not
really changed. We did get some feedback
on some language where we did make some
adjustments. Um, for example, some
people had asked if we had would add
therapeutic uh into some aspects of it,
be a little bit more um clear in some of
the language and so we have done that.
We are going to continue to go through
as with the other portions to sort of
see if there's any additional
clarifications. We did also adjust it to
make it a little bit more clear as far
as some of the areas where uh there were
some comments with regard to um changing
things a little bit with regard to um uh
uh what is different between the
facilitator and the therapist. And so we
did make some adjustments in there. For
example, with facilitator, we added on
in uh to the specific module things like
the pure facilitation ethics, how to
work as part of a care team, what it
means to be present with a patient.
really to be looking at those areas and
to clarify a little bit more that the
aspect about you know we're not asking
facilitators to be therapists but
ensuring that that is just from
anformational standpoint but talking
about some of the basic concepts of
psychotherapy
and then for example with the
practitioner certific certification
adding in a little bit more as far as
education of specific psilocybin
therapeutic modalities and working as
part of a care team as well to ensure
that that's in there.
Um
uh and then as I had kind of mentioned
earlier, we did add in on this version,
we do have the where we did make it so
that people who have the additional
trainings as far as basic life support,
we added in it could be an or with
cardoppulmonary resuscitation and AED
certification. Um, the other thing that
as I mentioned at the very beginning had
kind of come in from a couple of
different people. Um, and in fact I saw
another email just this morning that had
this request is to add EMS certification
into that list. And so we are going to
add EMS into this certification with
regard to the basic life support and
CPR.
And then the final part was the
continuing education requirements and
that has actually remained the same. um
with regard to the clinicians completing
a minimum of eight hours of CMEs and the
practitioners and facilitators um 20
hours and that is for every two years
for both of those and then I see we have
a couple of questions. So I'll start
with Larry.
>> Thank you Dom. I appreciate it. Um
I I don't think 25 hours dactic is
adequate for the um for the
practitioners if they haven't had
evidence of other training. I I think
that um there's a couple things. It's
well below like what any program in the
world that I have seen is like uh um
suggesting and I think by adding more
practicum we don't obiate the need for
more of the didactic. Um, and I I think
even just, you know, in our end of life
committee, you know, we actually think
that people need almost that much in end
of life if they're going to offer that.
So, I think there should be a a
reconvening of a meeting with people who
are either psychedelic therapists or
have been trained and and really go over
that because I think 25 is far from
adequate. I don't think it needs to be
150, but I think that's I think 25 is
too low.
>> Thank you, Larry.
Chris,
>> I agree with Larry that 25 hours of
dactic training doesn't seem nearly
adequate for
um any of these roles. And I'm also
concerned that
the training that the certifying
clinicians are going to have to take is
going to severely limit
um
the number of the already few uh people
with a
um
DEA license that are willing to
participate in this program.
and
ultimately I don't see
how facilitators are really going to be
utilized to any type of their potential
in this model. Um, this seems
to be very therapeutic centered and not
um allow people with
life experience to apply
uh peer support skills to this this
space.
>> Thank you, Chris. Desba
>> um just wanted to clarify the language
of adding the EMS uh component to it
that it is an in addition to as opposed
to as a like okay um
not an added on
additional must-have requirement but
that it is also considered as an
additional pathway. Does that make
sense? I just wanted to make sure that
that was a clarification between the
two.
>> Sure. Since that portion is not actually
in the text. Um, yes, Despa. It is an
or. So, for example, someone could have
basic life life support certification or
the CPR and AED certification or EMT,
EMS certification.
>> That was all. Thank you,
>> Brenda.
Brenda, if you're speaking, we can't
hear you.
>> I'm sorry. I agree that we should have
more practicum hours than less didactic.
Um that uh yeah, experience uh knowing
how to do all of this is uh crucial to
everything here.
and Ian.
>> So, I'm [clears throat] currently on the
fence about um more practicum or
didactic on only on the grounds that
these are already licensed professionals
that can provide a lot of aspects of
therapy. And so, it's not like we have
to they have to reinvent the wheel and
and learn how to redo everything. um
they do have to learn how to apply in
certain scenarios but they already have
a huge number of clinical hours that
they must go through in order to get and
maintain their lensure. So I I do
support that maybe it should be a little
higher than 25. I just don't think it it
needs to go crazy.
>> And one thing to clarify the 25 is for
that combined section. So that's the
portion that's the module that is both
practitioner and facilitator. There is
the additional five hours both in the
practitioner and the five the
facilitator which was how we had
presented it um last time. It's just it
got broken out into those two different
sections.
I'm sorry, Chris.
>> I think Larry was first. I'll let him go
first.
>> Sure, Larry.
>> Oh, Larry, if you're speaking, you're
still on mute.
>> Thank you. Seems like automute here. Um
so thank you about that. Um yeah I just
wanted to be clear I mean my
understanding the regulations is that um
people need to be um you know licensed
uh providers but for instance a
internist family doctor palative care
doctor. We're certainly not requiring
that people are all therapists. I would
not have the assumption that they have
you know two years of therapy training
there. That's really important mistakes.
I certainly don't think we should be
limited to that. And I also just want to
say that um having worked with a lot of
therapists and different people, this is
just a whole another ball game honestly.
I mean psychedelic therapy is really
different than CBT therapy or different
things. And and and I really do think
it's its own area. And I want to be
careful. I mean, you know, I mean, one
criticism that this would leave is very,
okay, it takes you um two years to be a
therapist, but if you want to be a
psychedelic therapist, it takes you 50
hours. Okay. So, I just I just want to
again advocate for more for for more
training and I liked Paul's idea that
looking at what each module might need
like what do you need to do end of life?
What do you need to do others? But
anyway, just to make that again.
>> Thank you, Larry. And then back to
Chris.
Uh again, I agree with Larry about
the requirements and the training level
for therapists and other mental health
professionals. I don't think this is
covered under their traditional training
in any way. Um although there is some
overlap in some sections of it, I guess.
Um, the other thing I want to bring up
is that we're offering reciprocity from
other state approved organizations and
we've literally like recreated the wheel
and this just seems like this there's
this dissonance between those two
things. Like
>> if we're saying that the other
states have
have done their due diligence and
um put together program training
programs
that can I'm sorry there's an echo. Can
somebody mute? Like all I can hear is my
own own voice.
>> Oh yeah. Sorry. Yeah. So Larry, the the
auto the thing that's automuting is me
sometimes because your mic feeds back a
lot. So if you could just um remember to
mute after you're done talking.
>> Thank you. Sorry. All right. Um it seems
like there's this dissonance between
those two ideas that we can offer
reciprocity because other states have
done uh done the work to certify these
training programs and then we're
completely going against everything that
those programs have put together. It
just doesn't make sense to me.
Yes,
>> hi. Sorry. Um, yeah, in that regard, you
know, cuz I had to again go like from
Massachusetts to New Mexico, I think
it's just more like a department thing
as far as my understanding is, you know,
we have to base our own rules on our own
like thoughts and ideas. And yes, it
would be great to have a consensus
amongst all the states of like what
we're going to do, but really I think it
just kind of comes down to these are the
rules and the regulations that we have
recommended or that we're stating, etc.,
you know, at the very end. Um and you
know it would be up to the deciding
person that you know they feel that
that's been covered with whatever
education whatever hours and and and
years of of being able to have done this
that the person who's seeking
reciprocity will be able to get like
it's granted through. Um but you know
moving forward like I I get that there's
a lot that we're trying to like hold
together at the same time. there's like
our rules, there's like state rules,
there's a reciprocity, there's like, you
know, life um experience and education
and what could be, you know, transfer to
this and you take a little bit out of
that. And I think just understanding
that like we're trying to find just a
middle ground of all those things and
not also like hold I mean we're holding
this dearly because this is going to
hopefully end up being the rules and the
regulations. But, you know, I understand
that it's it's a lot to try to like hold
together, you know, um and finding the
middle ground is is very difficult. But
at least in my understanding is that
reciprocity is is is that you know,
whatever is covered um based on the
number of hours. I mean, it's the same
for any job when you're trying to you
know, they require four bachelors for
four years, but you know, this person
has been working in this job for 20
years, but they don't have it. I mean,
it's up to that regulating thing
deciding, you know, is a 20 years of
life experience without a degree just as
important and as equivalent to four
years of like not having that life
experience, you know, is viable? I mean,
I know maybe that's not part of the
discussion, but that was just I I get
it. I get it's a lot to try to like hold
together.
Okay. Thank you everybody. I appreciate
it. Um just as a as a note with regard
to this is again parts of the hours are
we are hearing from wide variety of
different people. some who have said we
actually need should have more like two
or 300 hours and others who are saying
uh this should be very minimal for
example just a weekend on it and so we
are trying to figure out some of that
middle ground and trying to determine it
um and we'll continue to do that
throughout um not only the rule process
but also as the program continues to
develop and is implemented to ensure
that if there are things that need to be
adjusted that they are indeed adjusted.
Chris,
>> I I'm just curious like I've been to all
the training and education committee
meetings, I think, and I I haven't heard
that range coming across in those
committee meetings, and it seems like
where do I need to go to find the people
that are are talking about, you know,
these vastly different training
requirements?
Thank you Chris. Um some of those have
actually been in some of the meetings
where we have had people suggest that it
should just be uh you know that weekend
training would be sufficient for
individuals. Some of it has been in
other conversations that we've had,
including, for example, conversations
with, not that saying that that was your
viewpoint, but when we've had
conversations with you and other board
members and other members in the
community,
Brenda.
>> Oh, Brenda, I think you remuted
yourself. You were unmuted for a moment
there.
>> Oh, sorry. Um I think uh that uh
probably with the testing parts of it
like if you have experience uh I think
you know that should be one of the
questions that we should be asking
everyone. Have you had experience with
this medicine? And I think this this is
something that um I I don't think we've
really even talked a whole lot about in
any of these meetings because um uh it
would be great as a prerequisite.
But you know that's
that can open up a whole can of worms
there too. But I think um that should be
like one of the questions especially for
people who've had a lot of experience
with this medicine that um that should
be uh one of the questions in I guess
applying for uh you know uh this I I
guess it's going to wind up being a
license of some sort that uh it it
should be uh counted as as something
because a lot of people with experience,
that's all they're going to need is is a
weekend for,
you know, the uh uh practicum and other
people were going to need uh a lot more
practicum hours. So, I just wanted to
throw that out there for food for
thought.
Sorry, my I muted my mic and then forgot
to unmute it. Thank you, Brenda. Um,
Ian.
>> Yeah. So, I just wanted to kind of
bounce off that idea. I think we try to
get people with experience via the
reciprocity pathway. We can't just say
how many years of experience do you have
because everyone will have 100. Um so if
there's no way to verify so we I think
we're trying to use the reciprocity to
say hey if you can show me any
governmental tribal entity that said you
have practiced that we can validate we
can say um you know this was issued this
was apostial whatever mechanism that we
have to use versus um
asking for experience
I think is so uninverifiable
that it's [snorts] meaning is not really
there
but I'm happy to hear from everyone
else. Thank you.
>> Thank you Ian Desb.
>> Um on that note, two notes. Um and then
just as a reminder that this is you know
for the medical psilocybin pathway
um when it comes to people who are
interested in providing care through the
medical psilocybin pathway that is
regulated by New Mexico. Uh just leave
it at that. Um
and uh also time it is 9:48 and we
haven't even gotten to the other three
points. I propose that we maybe table
going through the rest of this. I will
just say that this is probably the
reason why in the previous meeting that
we had that we should have more
discussion on this because it's already
taken 40 minutes um to try to get just
through the reading. And I'm not I'm not
arguing that we shouldn't have done
this. I think that this was very needed
to be able to realize how much more
discussion we actually really need to
have on this. Um but just time 9:48.
>> Thank you Despa and uh Kenan you are
next. Thank you. I I realize that I am
just a covering uh designate. So I don't
want to drive policy here but I'll just
give this as a background.
There's going to be variability across
the board of whatever you try and
benchmark for training hours, right? And
so what I tried to do was think of
what's the most applicable clinical
situation we've seen in the past. And so
you might say the prescribing of
buprenorphine
uh which is a medication for opiate use
disorder can be used for pain etc. It
had a separate pathway than traditional
uh controlled substances. And so then
that has since been removed. But if you
look at the previous X-waver, the
X-waver required already licensed
professionals in the field. So, nurse
practitioners, physicians, assistants,
etc. So, similar to what you have here
to receive 24 hours of training just for
this one specific agent. And so,
I I'll just put that there for you guys
to make your own decision on, but I
think that's probably your best uh
benchmark that I can think of to to say
that this is kind of a standard used
without the medical facility. I
understand this is different. There are
different things that need to be taken
into account, but that's that's my two
cents and I'll be quiet.
Thank you, Kenan. I thought I saw
another board member with a hand up, but
I'm not sure who it was.
>> That was me. I just was going to say
that I I know we're coming to the
practicum next. So, I think that's one
of the things we wanted to hit.
>> Yes. And it is exactly. So, um unless
there's an objection, I'll move forward
to the practicum, which is part of one
of those main topics.
And so I'm putting that section into the
chat. Um, and so once again, uh, you
know, and there was a lot of
conversation with regard to this in the
last meeting. Um, and you know what
again it comes down to is we have sort
of flipped. I'm sorry, Chris.
>> Uh, no, go ahead. Go continue. I just
have a I know I'm going to have a
question right off the bat. So,
>> thank you. Um,
thank you Chris and I'll come back to
you then. Uh, I appreciate it. Um, and
so, um, anyway, with regard to this is
so, um, for the purposes of this, we do
still have that remaining the same. Some
of the questions that came up was the
amount of hours and part of this is
because, um, we have reduced down that
didactic. So we have kind of flipped it.
What we were hearing from various
members of the community is that the
practice was very important and that did
even come up during some of the the
meetings and talking about you know the
how many patients, how many people
really should be seen by facilitators
and practitioners to be able to get a
good sense of what was happening. And um
you know when we look at it you know
it's 100 hours as far as for the
practicum um with an additional 20 for u
the uh practitioners um and then and
that these can be completed as was asked
earlier in any of the um the approved
locations. So that includes healthcare
or I'm sorry um the um the facilities
andor uh other approved locations. So,
homes, things like that, temporary
locations as we have those. Um, so both
healing centers and other approved
locations. Um, and then, uh, the one of
the portions that has been brought up
and I see there's a question even about
it is the waiver of the practicum. And
so we did include that the waiver of the
practicum um or the practicum hours for
individuals who were doing reciprocity
so long as they were able to show um
that they did have um the 40 hours on
that reciprocity. And that's actually in
a different section, but I bring it up
here because one of the things that we
did add after talking with people in
hearing is to ensure that we did have
something similar for programs and
people who might be going through
training currently in New Mexico. And so
what we have added is the similar waiver
as far as those practicum hours. if
someone has been trained by a program
that is approved in New Mexico approved
by June 30th of 2027
and that that person would be able to
then meet those same requirements and
they would have to demonstrate the 40
hours of contact time which is the same
as what we have with regard to
reciprocity. Now again, part of this
with both reciprocity and for allowing
this with um New Mexico homegrown
programs is essentially to have those
minimum requirements to be able to do
this and to help build the
infrastructure for the program. And so
we think that by adding that on in then
we would have that actually extended uh
out there for that um that time period
which um if for example these rules um
are approved in the fall would provide
about 8 to 9 months with regard that to
that.
>> Now again this isn't the reciprocity
section. So, if we have items about
reciprocity, we'll get to those here
shortly.
>> I probably closed it.
>> No,
>> that's okay.
>> Okay, Larry.
>> Thank you, Dom. Um, yeah, I have a lot
of thoughts about the practicum to um uh
to share. Um, and I I bring part of this
from the experience of having done
practicum in um in another state. Um I
think I think there's a couple of things
that need to be looked at. One is that
um practicum in general does not happen
with people that have the diagnosis in
our program and I do not think it would
be appropriate for a um a novice to be
starting out doing sessions with people
with any of these four conditions. They
happen with people who are other
trainees. I think that's really
appropriate. It's safe. It's probably
less stress for everyone. And so I'm
strongly in favor and of a fix it bill
that actually allows for the training
using psilocybin for trainees that will
both would give some if some training
done doesn't have any psilocybin
experience they would gain that but
people could do that and I would suggest
that people are required to have two of
those sessions that would reflect what
Colorado does. Um the the other issue
that and again I'm in favor of uh a lot
of practical training was a few things.
One is the way it's written. You you
don't actually have to be doing
anything. It says you can just be
observing. So you could sit there your
whole eight hours observing if I'm
reading it correctly. So I'd like to see
it revised that say that you can start
out observing but you actually have to
be being observed and being you know
supervised you know at a certain point
in time. So you're not just sitting in a
room and not um you know not being um
observed. The other which is a big
concern is the costs for doing this. And
I think you really for the whole program
we need to look at some cost analysis.
Um when the people do the practicum in
Colorado the cheapest I've seen is it's
costing $2,200 and that's for um people
sitting for two sessions and having one.
So potentially we're talking about you
know a big expense. So I I think in
general we should start having a cost
effectiveness. We shouldn't be adding
anything without figuring out how much
it's going to cost. So those are my main
uh concerns. Make it available to be
done with trainees. Specify that when
people are doing that that some of it
actually has to be where you're actually
being the the uh the provider traininee
and then figure out how expensive it is.
Thank you very much.
>> Thank you, Larry. Um and just as a note
um that portion about them uh not just
sitting and watching observing it also
does include the conducting and that it
is supervised is actually in the first
paragraph of it uh in paragraph A. So
it's supervised practice and then the
opportunities to go through those.
>> Dom what I what maybe I'm reading this
wrong but it says to experience observe
or conduct. So I I don't see that
there's a that we're actually preventing
someone just observing.
>> Uh we can change that to and conduct.
>> That would be beautiful. Thanks, Val. I
appreciate that.
>> I appreciate it. Thank you.
Uh Chris,
>> yeah, I know we talked about this
before, but um can you explain why
there's the wording same day therapy
sessions in that? Again, this is a real
hangup for me. There there shouldn't be
therapy going on adjacent to a
psilocybin administration session.
>> Sure. Thank you, Chris. Um part of it is
because it is some of the language
within with regard to regulations and
potential billing um with the idea that
this these portions may be able um to be
build other than the administration
itself. So the administration portion as
we all know would not be able to be
build but the other hours potentially
could be build under some of the
therapeutic codes. We're still working
through some of that. And so that's part
of the reason for that language itself.
And we understand that it's uh and
that's a part of the training is that
this is sitting with the individual that
it should be patient centered that it
should be based upon the needs of the
patient and to an extent that is a part
of what therapy is. Um, and so that's
why it actually has that aspect there
because if we are able to get that that
approval for payments for those aspects
of the services, this language could be
very beneficial in that.
>> Yeah, I'm concerned it that it kind of
blurs the lines, but I'll let that go
for now. My next uh part is in here you
have um students participate in or
observe preparatory and integrative
therapy sessions like that. This is
another
spot where we are
not acknowledging that facilitators
might have a role in this process at
all. Um because not all preparation or
integration is therapy.
Um,
and then
I guess I'm also kind of hung up on the
difference between integrative therapy
and post-integrative therapy.
I'm sorry, Chris. Maybe that's just
because it's the post integration
therapy simply refers to the sessions
that happen after administration.
So it's the you know basically the the
preparation sessions and then the post
integration therapy.
So the post just refers to the time
frame of when they occur.
Okay, Larry.
>> Yeah, Chris brings up something and I
just may need clarity myself, but is
there anything here that prevents a fac
a facilitator from doing the integration
sessions by themselves? Is there a
requirement that the licensed provider
is present at all of the facilitator
sessions? And and I guess the other way
to deal with some of what Chris is
bringing up if it some of us could say
therapy/facilitation
sessions, but I think we I need
clarification on on the question if the
if the facilitator can do the
facilitation without the licensed
provider there.
>> I'm sorry, Larry. You're asking if the
facilitator can do the sessions without
the practitioner.
>> Is that correct?
>> The integration session. Yes.
>> Yeah. Again, there's nothing in the rule
that actually stops that.
>> Okay, good. Because I I think it may be
appropriate for that to happen with the
with the licensed provider not being
present at all the all the integration
sessions. Thank you.
>> Right. And as a note, this is just as it
pertains um with regard to practicums.
And so that separate section the two the
part B is really just the additional
um uh or I'm sorry is just the the
allocation that the students so that's
both practitioners and facilitators
having at least 20 of those hours being
with regard to the preparation and
integration sessions.
>> Thanks for the clarification. It does
sound it answers the question if the
facilitators can have integration
without the license provider, but we
might want to make sure we're clear
about that as well.
>> Yes.
>> Outside of practicum.
>> Sure,
Chris.
>> Yeah. So,
that's
I'm curious why there has to be the
therapy sessions language in this
section. We can we can do this all with
preparatory and integration
and how that looks is up to the care
team and in the rules it makes it appear
like this needs to be done by the
therapist or this is therapy which is
not always the case. Sure, we can take
that language out then, Chris. Uh,
especially in this because, you know, we
do define what the integration or the
post integration sessions are. Uh, it's
really just a descriptor, but if that
makes you feel more comfortable, we can
take that on out. Uh, and as you can
see, I'm doing that right now. Thank
you. Does that help?
>> Yes. Thank you.
>> Okay. Thank you. And I appreciate it.
you know, we do want to ensure that we
have, you know, that we have this as to
be inclusive. None of it is meant to be
exclusive.
>> Okay, Dez.
Um, it just seems like a lot of the
conversation, and I'm not disregarding
what anyone's saying, it's all very
important, but I'm just it seems like
that a lot of the conversation is like a
billing
word language issue and understanding
that this is a medical psilocybin
pathway that is being regulated by New
Mexico. And as much as a lot of us I can
I'm assuming speaking for a lot of us
whereas we realize that these um
sessions these journeys and our own
experience in coming to the medicine has
not been and does not look as clinical
as what it sounds like that that is that
is correct that is not like necessarily
I feel like this is a middle ground
pathway between western medicine and
government saying this is wrong you're
sinful, you're a horrible person for
doing this and you're going to be thrown
in jail. And then there's also the other
side of it. So completely two different
spectrums and that this is a middle
ground. like where do these two converge
the confluence between these two com
vastly different uh ways of thinking and
finding that middle ground will be you
all are we're all doing you all are
doing a very good job of understanding
that yes now we have to do billing um
language and understanding where that
western model and way of thinking is
coming in to meet with hey I don't
remember being regulated and regul um
you know had this many practicum hours,
you know, years ago or whenever the last
session that I or anyone else has had.
Um, so just kind of wanted to point that
out.
>> Thank you, Desba. Uh, Ian,
>> thank you, Desba. I really appreciate
what you said. Um but I do want to just
point out since we are here uh two of
the I mean one of the things we were
discussing um and that we had pulled
aside was the practicum hour volume.
Since we are still here I just want to
redraw everyone's attention to that
practicum hour volume. um
what changes would we like to see there?
Cuz that was kind of a an area where we
hadn't fully resolved.
Larry.
>> Yeah, I may be being slightly
repetitive, but I don't think we can
actually resolve that without um the um
legislative bill that allows for people
to be able to work as trainees. I think
the numbers are not realistic without
that. I think with that they become more
realistic. So, I I think they're they're
linked in issues. And I know it's
awkward because we can't as a group be,
you know, making and proposing bills,
but I I do think that's that's linked
into this question.
>> Thank you, Larry. Chris,
>> I know a lot of people want to see the
hours reduced for the practicum, but
unless the we balance that with the
shift to the dactic hours, I don't think
that would be responsible at all. And so
if we are
willing to open up discussion back on
that section then maybe we can find a
little bit more balance. But
um as it stands now I think that's the
only thing that will actually
help train our people.
>> Thank you Chris Ian.
Thank you, Larry and Chris. All righty.
So, um, if we need to make changes to
the dactic, that's fine, but we just
need to come up with a consensus within
the law um, in order to provide a
program. So
assuming that the law doesn't change at
least until January
um on a good day um we have to find so
how does the board feel because I've
heard from Chris I've heard from Larry
about the hour requirement but I haven't
heard from pretty much anyone else and I
just want to in in regards to that
specific thing I have heard from you
guys I and not listening. But um in
regards to those hours, so I just kind
of want to see how everyone's feeling
>> Dan. Yeah, thank you. I uh did not know
prior to this what was the didactic
hours requirement before this draft of
this rule
>> that was proposed? Oh, they it was the
same hours. The dactic has not changed
on it. The only thing that changed was
we shifted it to break it out into a
couple other into those other mod that
other module for the practitioners.
>> Okay, good. Because I think I might have
just misunderstood. I for some reason I
thought that these practicum hours had
similar hours in the didactic hours as
well, meaning that it would be double
the amount of time. So I feel personally
with this because I hear a lot of people
saying that the number of hours required
is very low on the didactic but I wonder
if the so is there a balance between the
two. Is there is everybody okay with the
number of hours for the practicum but
the dactic is low or that the practicum
should be less and the dactic more? Um I
I feel that a lot of the practicum
brings in a lot of what the didactic has
taught and is then practiced. That's and
again I'm coming from this is naive to
me. So I'm just bringing this in from my
you know own naivity. So I I'm okay with
the hours as long as it is the true
practice of those things that was
learned in the classroom.
>> Thank you Dan Brenda.
Um I think with the didactic there
there's going to be a lot of learning
like book learning with the didactic and
teaching there. Um where the rubber
meets the road here is practicum. Um
people
if if you're if you're learning
something in a classroom it's totally
different than hands-on.
And so the hands-on is going like Dan
said, it is a learning experience in
itself. So um I would like to see just a
little bit more of the practicum hours.
Um the didactic is going to come with
all of the learning that has to be done
here in the ed education and the the the
curriculum. So, uh, I I you're going to
learn by doing hands-on and that's
that's how um I've always had practicum
done that way being thrown in and you
know, you do it and that's how you
learn. Um, but yes, I I I agree with Dan
that, you know, there there has to be a
little bit balance, but I'm leaning more
towards more practicum hours.
Thank you, Brenda. Ian,
>> and I just want to say I agree with
Brenda. Uh, when I was in nursing
school, we um when you're taught
something on a on a PowerPoint,
everything is in a perfect world. The
patient only has one condition. They're
only on one medication. Um, and it's so
easy to deal with. Um, but when you
actually get into the hospital room and
you have to look at an e uh an ECG where
the they're breathing so it's messing
with the line and it's not adhered
correctly and you actually have to
interpret, that's where learning really
happens because in the classroom it's
too normal. It's too
focused on just trying to show you the
one condition. And I agree the where the
craziness comes from is the practicum
where that dealing with adverse
experiences is practicum at least from
my nursing experience.
>> Thank you Ian Larry.
>> Yeah it's actually really different than
the way you're describing in a
casilocybin session. The typical
psilocybin session, the person is within
for most of the whole six hours. There's
very little conversation. You're just
basically holding space, learning how to
provide their needs, whether to go to
the restroom. Occasionally, something
comes up, but but there's not a lot of
it's not like taking care of like a a
person in a hospital. It very much is
they're within and you're just sitting
there holding space. So, I I don't think
that teaching that you're describing
actually is happening there. It happens
more in the prep and the integration.
Some of what I think is important in the
dactic has to do with our four specific
conditions. So that people like about
end of life. I mean some of the
important issues are like making sure
that there's adequate family support.
They're they're issues that don't really
come up during the session. So I'm just
pushing back a little bit on the idea
that the practicum is it's not like the
same as a nursing training. I think it I
think it's different here. And usually,
honestly, regardless of what number of
sessions we have, there's an excellent
chance that no one will have um you
know, certain like anything that's they
may have a challenging personal
experience, but they're unlikely to have
something that's like a adverse event
type experience.
So, they need to be prepared for that
didactically.
>> Thank you, Larry.
Chris,
>> I just wanted to say I agree with Larry
and there's a lot that goes into this
didactically that adds to your overall
knowledge and just preparedness for this
uh whole experience that you you
might not get from um I mean eventually
you'll get it through practical
experience but I think there's some uh
hard lessons that you
could avoid through
um a little bit more didactic learning.
Thank you Chris.
So the one thing I will say is again as
we were looking at what the hours really
both for practicum and the dactic, it
was about balancing because we were
hearing in various uh committee meetings
and also in other conversations with
people that you know different people
have vastly different perspectives that
the dactic was too much or too little,
the practicum too much too
And so really we did try to thread that
needle and try to come up with as good
of a balance as possible. Um and so
that's really what we've done here. And
of course if there are some adjustments
we do understand that. Um but again it
was to try to figure out what would be
that balance and we did hear from quite
a lot of people that it was practical
experience and that the biggest concern
was really about being able to complete
the hours um in a time frame as well as
the cost. And that's a part of why we
didn't want to really exceed um you know
too many hours combined between the two
different types. And so that's just a
part of where and why we have them at
this point. But again, if the board
feels, you know, that some adjustments
should be or could be made, then
definitely we can look into that.
So why don't we go ahead and take a
vote? If you are not okay with the
current minimum practicum hours, please
raise your hand at this time. Again, if
you are not okay um with the current
practicum hours, please raise your hand.
Point of clarification, Dominic. Do we
need to second and follow Robert's rules
for this? I apologize. I don't know the
process.
>> Um, that's up to the board.
>> Okay.
>> Clarify because it gets confusing when
you're putting the knot in there. Is the
move to approve as they are?
>> So, the move is okay.
Do we need further discussion on like do
we need to change something or are
people okay with it? So he was in
objection to the current
practicum hours.
I'm willing to vote for the current
hours. I just want to be clear that I
think it's not practical until we have a
bill that allows people to work with
trainees and that I think that we need
to actually figure out the costs of this
and I'm concerned that we haven't
actually done those two.
>> All right. So again, I'll rephrase that.
Um, any objections?
>> I am opposed to the current educational
standards as they exist. And if I have
to vote against the practicum hours for
to state that, then that's what I'm
going to do.
>> I guess to clarify too because I'm also
against the current dactic hours. So is
that a vote no on this or are we just
talking about the practicum in this
vote?
So, we're working on just the the
practicum hours. Um, if you have any
objections to the practicum hours, raise
your hand.
>> Alrighty. And please lower your hands.
And Ian, just as a a clarification for
the public is this is just for board
members.
>> All right. So, it looks like we have two
that are in objection of the current
rules or of the current practicum hour
requirements. Um,
is everyone okay with moving to adopt
these practicum hours for the time being
minus those two? Obviously,
>> I I would like it to be noted that I do
not think that this is feasible without
an additional bill and that that's my
strong recommendation. So maybe it's an
abstension at this point in time.
Without objection, the record shall
reflect that you uh requested a
amendment to the legislation in order to
properly affectuate
>> these um practical mowers.
>> Thank you again. I appreciate that very
much.
>> All right, Brenda,
you're muted.
[laughter]
Still muted.
Brenda, you you're muted at the moment.
If you could unmute yourself.
>> What is this? Yeah, I agree with Larry.
I agree with Larry on this that that we
need just a little further discussion on
this and I think we'll be able to kind
of um get some balance here on uh what
we need to do here. And if I may, um, we
do have the section in there if you
notice, and I had mentioned it just very
briefly, but down in section G, which
does allow for the department to wave or
suspend the practicum hours as needed in
order to help build the initial
infrastructure. And some of that was
included in based upon, for example,
what Larry is talking about. uh and to
do that. And so it would be the
situation that if as the program is
implemented, it does indeed show that
doing these minimum hours is too
honorous um or expensive or other.
I think Dominic froze.
I concur with that.
>> I thought it was me, so I'm glad it's
not.
>> Oh,
>> there we go.
>> You're back.
>> Am I back?
>> Am I back? Okay, I'm back. Thank you.
Uh, sorry. Uh, Dr. uh uh uh Dr. Rob was
handing me his headphones so that I
could speak through his mic, but um
thank you everybody. I'm not sure where
it where I had frozen, but basically
what I was saying is exactly for the
purposes that Larry, for example, was
bringing up is that we do have section
G, which is a waiver of practical
requirements. so that if we found that
some of these practicum requirements
were honorous or too expensive or any of
those, the program could actually wave
them um in order and if for example
legislative changes or things like that
um in order to help facilitate the
building of the infrastructure for the
program. And so we did put that in
specifically for some of these concerns
um because we did want to ensure that as
things are implemented that if we have
to make adjustments we can and we can do
that as a reduction without having to go
back through the rulem process at that
point.
I hope everybody was able to hear all of
that. Did I freeze again?
Yes.
>> Yeah. I think I think we heard all that.
>> Yes.
So is the question on whether or not we
want to vote uh versus table the
discussion. Is that where we left off? I
think the the freeze threw off the flow
unfortunately.
>> Yes. So the question was whether we
wanted to vote on this or continue
discussion. So if you would like to vote
at this time, please raise your hand.
All right. And then if you would like to
table this for later discussion, please
raise your hand.
With a unanimous vote, we tabled the
practicum hours.
And you can lower your hands at this
time.
>> Ian, just just to be clear, I think some
of us may be voting because it's it's
the dactic hour. So, I think you're
getting a mixed vote on here.
Uh, okay. So,
if I may, the real question that we just
need to know is, do we have the
permission to continue to move forward
with regard to this? And so and and
again I would say just with regard to
the practicum hours with understanding
that yes there potentially could be
changes. We are still working with you
know and continuing [snorts] to have
conversations with regard to it. Um and
um you know uh and as far as the hours
again as we've talked about if some of
those need to change we're we're we've
been asking and so what I would really
suggest is what type of hours people
would need on that. So um I'll leave it
to you all to decide if you know if this
is getting tabled or if we are moving
forward.
Larry.
>> Yeah. I just wonder if if given given
this whether this would be appropriate
to go back to the um subcommittee to
actually have a focused discussion which
might easily take like an hour about
what we're recommending as number of
hours if that seemed reasonable and
Donna I would ask you whether that would
be problematic in the timing of the
process to take the time I think it'd be
worth it to try to have um you know have
more of an agreement among the advisory
board.
>> Thank you Larry. Um, just as a note, if
it's simply talking as far as number of
hours, I think that those can definitely
be adjusted as the process continues to
move forward.
Chris.
>> Yeah. I I don't think we can separate
these issues. If we lower the
if we lower the practicum hours without
balancing it with the dactic somewhere.
Um and it I feel like those are
wolffully inadequate to begin with. like
all of this is connected and there's
accessibility issues that also come up
for me in this with how many patients
are actually going to be available for
people to do practicums and I I just
think that um we need to think this
through more thoroughly.
>> Thank you Chris Dan.
>> Thank you. Yeah, I'm gonna echo Dr.
Leman and Chris on this. I think that it
does make sense to go back to the
committee but for both the didactic and
the practicum but on a very legitimate
not like I think it should be more it
should be this and I think there needs
to be a definitive consensus to the
number of hours um but because I think
we just get into this and go I feel it
should be more I feel it should be less
there needs to be a specific and those
numbers are arbitrary but there needs to
be at least some consensus on those
numbers Um because there's no reason for
us to split hairs here in my opinion.
>> Thank you, Dan. Ian,
>> um I would say I think we should just go
ahead given that we already pushed back
the reciprocal deadline to June. Um
we
this should not be that large of an
issue and if it does start to create you
know a systemic barrier we would see
that before the rules to allow the
easier out of state um mechanisms to
take over. So, I think we have so much
time that we can allow it. Otherwise,
again, we're getting into the issue of
we're
when you're picking arbitrary numbers,
kind of like Dan said, it's always going
to just kind of well, I feel this way, I
feel this way, cuz I have also been in
the training and education meetings, not
all of them, but most of them. um to say
to hear the swaying of back and forth
that the 120 has gone through um to get
there. And so I fear sending it back to
committee is just going to end up with
another number and then we're going to
end up feeling different at that time.
Thank you, Larry.
>> Um, I I I would agree with Dan's um that
it goes back to the committee with a
very specific focus and the charge of
sorting out the number of issues. I
would also suggest an approach be used
that we use an end of life committee
which is to bring in several experts and
I think we could do that. We could
invite someone from California Institute
of Integral Studies. Let's just not have
it sort of like a I think you think.
let's bring in some people that have
experience and ideally don't have uh you
know any kind of a commercial conflict
and inform that. We found that very
helpful in the end of life committee to
to bring in some experts to to to do
that.
>> Thank you Larry.
>> So what I'm hearing regardless is that
to send it back to the committee.
Okay. Well, and I believe we have a
there is an educational and training
committee meeting uh that is set for um
the next Friday the 17th.
>> Correct.
Uh we could uh would you like to bring
Well, we could talk about it there, but
um uh never mind.
>> [laughter]
>> Thank you, Brenda. Um, Keenan,
>> yeah, I I would just say so that um to
continue this to help get to a
discussion like Dr. was saying,
is it sufficient to have people from
another state and would that be the
accepted authority the board members
feel comfortable with? Is there any
benchmarking to other license types uh
medical cannabis, end of life that
should also be used? just be very clear
here right now what those pieces are to
make the decision there so that the
cycle can the decision can be made and
and you guys move forward is is all I
suggest.
>> Thank you Kenan Ian.
>> So I guess my suggestion would you guys
like to flip the training and education
the medical psilocybin advisory board
meeting on the 17th? Um that way the
training and education goes first and
then we can review whatever they come up
with if they come up with a resolution
to this issue.
>> Just to clarify, Ian, are you talking
you're talking about switching the times
on Friday that those meetings are
happening, correct?
>> Right.
>> Yes. Okay.
Brenda, you had your hand up.
Uh,
>> yeah. I just got a little confused.
That's all.
Larry, Ian, Ian, this I say this with
total respect for you, but I I think
that you you're hearing from your board
that they want to have us go back to the
committee and have a discussion and a
plan. And I don't think you're hearing
that they want to have it all figured
out by next week. And so I would ask you
to respect the the opinion and and as
the chair
>> to clarify I do respect the opinion. I
was trying to allow the difference to
the training and education committee
before our next meeting since they were
scheduled on the same day. But thank
you.
>> Thanks Ian. I appreciate it.
>> All righty. and then we can continue
Dominic. Um [clears throat]
>> okay. Uh the the next aspect and this
one is uh is uh the educational program
and continuing
um with uh mentoring requirements um and
their recordeping. And so the
recordkeeping is of course pretty
standard. Uh keeping their syllabi, all
of that information. Um and of course
you know items such as start and
completion date for students. Um and
then the mentoring requirement and this
has not changed since earlier or since
the previous discussion is that the
educational programs would need to uh
provide students after they graduate
with a minimum of 10 hours of mentoring
um mentoring sessions and so that that
has uh has not changed on there. Are
there any questions with regard to this
this section?
Okay. And then the next part and this
was the the next section um really for
discussion and this is on reciprocity.
Um and uh
as I had kind of mentioned earlier, we
did have a little bit of changes with
this. Um and the main one that we did is
as I mentioned in the beginning is
including the aspect for programs that
are current um in New Mexico that are
starting up here and for allowing them
um to be able to um to to also
essentially have reciprocity. Um and
then we do have the waiver of the
practicum requirements for recip
reciprocity. They do still have to show
that they have 40 contact hours with
with regard to this uh with regard to
psilocybin uh treatments. Um and then
again as mentioned earlier is it also
does have that waiver so that the
department if this does indeed show
prove to be an issue or a concern the
department can wave some of those
practicum requirements if needed. Um and
then outlining just how those programs
actually get approved is essentially
they get submitted um as a as an
individual is requesting that
reciprocity. they submit that the
document uh or that the program is
either already on the list and as we've
said stated we did include and specify
that if it is a program already approved
in Oregon or Colorado um that that would
be uh automatically on that list. um but
also allows for other possibilities
including for example um other states as
other states get uh have psilocybin and
medical psilocybin programs that they
also could be uh approved. Um and then
it has the same same um certification
timeline as far as for educational
programs in the state as far as they
would be have a two-year approval um it
once they were approved. So once a
program is on the list, they have a
2-year approval for that.
So that way if uh other individuals
later on are submitting their
reciprocity, they don't have to submit
all of the other requirements.
Despa,
>> uh, just a reminder, when was when were
these um going to be presumably rolled
out to have people applying by the
December 31st deadline? And then also
time, it's 10:36.
>> Yes, thank you. I appreciate it, Despa.
And um, as to the first question is, you
know, if we are able to move forward,
um, then we would be looking at this
being implemented in the fall. And so it
would give individuals several months to
be able to complete these requirements.
And again, this is for people who have
already graduated from other locations
after the December 31st deadline. The
reciprocity stays the same with the
exception that um they would need at
that time to complete the full practicum
hours required in New Mexico, whatever
those end up being.
Uh Dan,
>> can I ask a question because again my na
naivity on this. So in other states the
patients or the qualifying individuals
in those states are not necessarily
patients like we would have here meaning
end of life uh uh drug resistant um uh
excuse me. Anyway, the the four that we
have. So, is there any concern that we
have that the 40 hours that they have in
another state
doesn't necessarily fit the patients we
would have? Just just worth the
question.
>> Absolutely. Thank you, Dan. Um, this
really is a compromise. um we need to in
many ways start somewhere and so we did
make this match with what we're doing
for the you know the New Mexico based
programs as well for that first time
frame except the time frame for this to
accept it with just the 40 hours is uh
shortened of course because it's only
till the December and again if the board
feels we should extend that on out we
can and that's also where the waiver of
the practicum requirements if the
department feels we have to push that
forward a little bit make that a little
bit later in order to help some
individuals to be able to practice in
New Mexico who've already been
practicing and gone through the
training, we can do so. Um, so that's a
great question. um there's always
anytime there's a new program starting
that there's you know that possibility
and so I think this is a good compromise
um to ensure that there is uh some of
those considerations with regard to what
people have already done in other states
and you know what what we're going to be
requiring for programs here internally
as well.
I hope that helps.
Okay, Chris.
So, I had thought we had uh changed the
dates that we were going to accept
reciprocity
till
June somewhere, but I'm seeing in here
for the practicum hours that that is
still December 31st is or is that
>> uh that was for the internal so New
Mexico based programs that we put it at
the June mark. But again, you know,
we're we can consider extending this on
out further. That wasn't uh and it may
have been something that someone had
recommended through the chat in the last
one, but it wasn't one at least that I
had heard as far as a change when we had
the discussion last.
Um,
so I think
people that are just beginning programs
in other states are going to have a hard
time even meeting this timeline for
practicum
um or even an approved program for
reciprocity.
So I think we should extend the
deadlines out.
>> Are there objections to that?
So, and Chris, I'm assuming you meant to
the June 30th,
>> either the June or December 27 when the
programs was meant to roll out
um initially.
>> Uh Larry, thank you, Chris, by the way.
Thank you, Larry.
>> Oh, Larry, you are still muted.
>> Third times a charm. Um, so the um um I
I'm involved with because we send people
to other programs for our research. What
Chris says is really true. I mean, at
this point in time, the next cohorts are
starting in the fall. They won't finish
till like March of 27 and then it takes
a while to get the practicum done. And
so I think, you know, actually December
31st, 2027 would be reasonable because I
think people should have the ability to
start the program, you know, at this
point since they haven't had any
guidance up till now.
>> The one thing I would just suggest is if
we do that to 2027 that we do the same
with regard to the New Mexico programs.
And
>> I would agree with that, Don.
>> Okay. And so if that's the case, unless
there's objection from people, cuz
again, this is just sort of reviewing
and no objection here.
Okay. Uh Ian,
>> I don't have an objection. I can wait a
second.
>> Sure. No, no, it sounds like there's
none. So, we'll make those changes and
we'll go back to the other section and
make those changes as well. Um but go
ahead, Ian.
Yeah, I just wanted to actually
um remind that December 31st is not the
original deadline. It's what's known as
a legislative backs stop. Meaning if we
are getting close to that date and we
have not finished the program, we have
not done our jobs. So, I just want that
reminder there that that is not the goal
date, that is the hard deadline when we
have to have this program implemented.
Um, that's why we're okay with saying,
okay, maybe we can try for earlier
because we can absolutely not try for
later.
Just as housekeeping too, we've got a
little over 15 minutes right now left
for the meeting, just as a reminder.
>> Thank you, Johnny. Um, you beat me to
it. And so I was going to ask, are there
any other questions with regard to this?
Okay. And so um and again just uh with
regard to with the time uh the next
sections actually have not changed um
and it's really just about the testing
out of the dactic portions um and then
as well as uh the prohibitions as far as
for certifying clinicians um
facilitators and practitioners um that
really just again that uh a patient
can't be treated by someone they're
related to. for example. Um and um and
then as far as for the testing out,
that's really just that the educational
programs have to offer a way for people
to be able to test out. Okay. Um and
next is uh Desba. And by the way, Desba,
if you're asking as far as that third
part, it's actually just in the next
section.
>> Oh, no. [laughter]
Um, I was I would just say for for
thoughts on on this deadline issue, is
it easier to have an earlier deadline
and then be able to move it up as
opposed to having a later deadline and
then pushing it back? Like so for
instance, is it better to have keep it
at December 1st and then, you know, if
we need to revise, move it up to March
or is it better to have it further out
and then be like, "Oops, we really
should have moved this back to
December." just as a like you know
departmental logistics.
>> Sure. To be honest it it really was is
they were based off of suggestions from
various people as far as what they
thought length of time would be and but
the December 31st 27 is not problematic.
>> Yeah. I guess I guess I'm just like, you
know, as we're moving forward, um if we
need to revise something, is it easier
to have the deadline at December 31st
and say like we actually need to extend
it down to March of 2027? Is that is
that like an easier fix as opposed to
starting out later and moving it back? I
>> I think in this particular case it's not
uh not a problem. Yeah, in some areas it
would be, but I think for this one
that's not an issue. It's a great
question. Thank you though.
>> Uh Larry,
>> yeah, it's maybe moot, but I I think the
reason to give that date now is so
people can feel comfortable enrolling in
the programs and knowing they'll have
enough time to to get it done because it
is a commitment for people. So, I think
if we let them know they have till
December 27, they'll be more comfortable
making their life plans.
Right.
Okay.
Okay. And so uh the next step is um
application processes. Um and so the
first part this is just the general
portion of it. And so I'll do this
portion first. um uh which is
uh really just the applications have to
go through the electronic system that we
will be developing um and are in the
process of doing um and that they'll
have to do renewals every 2 years um for
their certifications and then just uh
really again that they may voluntarily
relinquish their certification at any
time just by providing written notice.
Um and uh that they consent that people
who are certified and organizations
consent to have their contact
information published uh through the
department. Oh, and I'm sorry, I copied
it into the chat but forgot to hit send.
My apologies everyone.
Any questions with regard to that?
Okay. And then the next part are the
specifics. Now, for a lot of the
different applications, they are pretty
much the same. So, I will um I'm just
going to go over the one here because
this is the one where we do have uh the
additional questions and it's with
regard to the certifying con clinician.
Um, and this one, what we do have on
this, and this is where the questions
keep uh keep coming up, is that the
certifying clinician, oh, and I should
note that we did hear, by the way,
people were saying they didn't like the
term diagnostic clinician, that they
felt that it didn't cover everything.
So, we did change that to certifying
clinician um throughout the rules and um
uh or the proposed rules. And so, we did
make that change on there. Um so thank
you for those suggestions. Um and um but
with regard to this essentially what
everybody need would need to do is do
the completed W9 form, the documentation
of their professional license um de uh
and then the completion of the
certifying clinician training
requirements um or that they have tested
out of the didactic portions. um
documents of continuing ed uh if it's a
renewal. Um and then uh as attestation
um with regard to uh not being a
registered sex offender and that we will
deny or revoke if someone is and then
their um certificate or verification of
results of their New Mexico controlled
substance number. Um and then their
personal data which is really just to
track and ensure it's the same person
which is date of birth, driver's
license, phone, legal names,
affiliation, consent forms. Um so the
area that uh and the others are very
similar um have essentially the same
items. The main difference and I'll put
that in the chat is what we were talking
about before is about ensuring that um
in the other cases they have their basic
life support or CPR or as I mentioned
before came in after we had sent this on
out the EMT training certification. Um
and uh and of course HIPPA
certification. Um otherwise the others
are all the same. The difference being
that with the the clinician, the
certifying clinician is the New Mexico
controlled substance number. And I know
there's been a lot of question about
that, about why we are requiring that
that some of the other licenses have the
ability to um to be able to diagnose
some of the conditions. And yes, that is
true. Um for example, social worker can
diagnose with regard to PTSD and
depression, for example. But the main
reason for the controlled substance
number is because it is a treatment that
is occurring with a medication. And so
with that, the certifying individual, in
this case, the clinician, does need to
have a controlled substance number. And
that's something that, you know, with it
being a medical program, that is part of
what ensures that there is that medical
evaluation, that medical certification
to be able to have it. with regard to
this. And so, um, at this point, uh, any
questions
or comments?
Okay, Chris,
I've got several, but uh, I think we'll
start out with,
um, some of the liability issues. I
think with this I I am concerned that
putting the access point through a
doctor is going to
um
make it very risky for clinicians to
certify anybody into this program
because they're going to be, you know,
subject to malpractice.
uh I believe and I think all the
liability should lie in the room where
the patients being treated because
ultimately all the risk mitigation comes
from proper preparation
administration techniques and
integration techniques and if we
um why would a why would a clinician
sign off on a patient when he's not
going to be necessarily in the room. Um,
when all of that happens and when
something goes wrong, the last thing I
want to see is everybody doing this, I
think it needs to be very clear where
the liability lies. Um
the access issues for this are I just
think very
um
it it troubling like my wife hasn't been
able to get a a primary care
practitioner for [snorts] over a year
now and we live in Albuquerque and she's
got great insurance through San labs. Um
the access outside of Bernal Leo County
is going to be just
unattainable.
Um
I I think you all keep pointing towards
cannabis as a how this program rolls
out. um saying we can do the same thing,
but I see a major issue with the
propagation
piece of that. In cannabis, you get a
user or a patient through and certified
into the program and now they've become
a daily user. And so the supply chain
stuff um just doesn't work out when you
have somebody who might be using a half
an ounce a year if they continue to come
back.
So,
um there's just a, you know, massive
program sustainability aspect to that
and
um I think
with the huge shortage of primary care
or people with these licenses in New
Mexico,
um coupled with the the amount of risk
and the training that they have to take
to enter the program, it's just going to
make this completely unaccessible and I
think it uh I think it completely kills
this program and uh I would recommend
that we look towards a model of
consultation
um where
the practitioners
are required to consult with
um
to to determine medical readiness in
circumstances where that's necessary. It
allows for continuity of care for
practitioners to uh work with doctors
that are already treating patients and
um I think it solves a lot of these
issues of liability and accessibility.
Thanks.
>> Thank you, Chris. Uh Dan,
>> I have to really lift up what Chris
said. um from rural area. My big
concern, and I know we're not at this
point yet, but it's further down in the
document as I'm reading it, is that I
would have to find this person who is a
doctor who has a CS who has gone through
the program and I physically have to
travel to them. um to certify a patient,
certifying clinician must have an
clinical client relationship with the
patient um and conduct an in-person
physical or mental evaluation. So
therefore, I would have to find that
person who was going to be in
Albuquerque or Santa Fe, maybe even Los
Cruises, but it won't be here. Um and I
could not do it via Tela. Uh the only
time I could is if I get reertified. So
therefore I I feel that from an
equitable standpoint I don't I feel that
I would be very limited from where I sit
in my home here from that. Plus if
you're a provider that or if you're a
patient that isn't end of life that
means that end of life patient must go
to that phys physician that is in that.
So I I mean I'm sure that they might be
part of the same team but and I'm not
assuming that in every part of the state
that would be the way that that would
work. So if my mom who died of cancer
would need to go and get this, she would
physically not be able to be in this
program. So
>> thank you Dan Ian.
In a rare turn of events,
I'm going to side with them on the
grounds that uh upon doing my
evaluations, psilocybin appears very
safe. And one of the models I was
comparing it to was the Washington DC
medical cannabis model which allows you
to self-certify. So what if we could
provide them with a list of
contraindications say hey do you got any
of this? If they say no then we can move
them on. Um
I do in a perfect world I would love to
have everyone have access to someone
with a New Mexico controlled substances
number. in an ideal world um everyone
would have access to health care but
unfortunately this is the real world and
I think that um even some of the
conditions that my committee in uh
patient qualification and safety has
been looking at was existential distress
um associated with a lifelimiting
illness that's not in the DSM5 that
doesn't need to be vet to be done by
someone with diagnostic potential I
could self-certify I yes I have been
living with existential distress. I have
uh have treatment resistant depression.
I tried XYZ. So I think um that could
allow more access um in the program as
well. Thank you.
>> Thank you Ian. Brenda,
>> um I too uh agree with Ian on on this
point and everyone else on the uh panel
here that um it just seemed to be this
whole week was me trying to find doctors
and psychiatrists
uh for my patients. Um currently uh for
example for uh Aderall um the the hoops
that people have to jump through just to
get the medical
uh clearance and then try to find a
psychiatrist to prescribe because
doctors don't want to prescribe um at
all. There's quite a few of them that
will push that onto the psychiatrist. by
the time uh I see my client, we're we're
looking at anywhere between 3 and 6
months of this type of bottleneck that
that's been happening. So, um yeah, to
uh as Ian said, this is the real world
and I think that we we need to think all
of this again.
>> Thank you. Uh Kenan
>> uh just throwing out some some
possibilities. Is is it a possible to to
only all behavioral health providers and
allow through tele medicine? Would that
be a meaningful compromise um
to allow some sort of uh recommendation
um or or referral uh without
uh being restrictive? Um, I remember
back seeing patients, we actually had to
fill out referrals and medical marijuana
cards and that had to be an in-person
signature on a piece of paper, right?
So, I understand that's barri and not
wanting that. Um, but it does provide
some level of referral and oversight
that that occurs. Um, and some
therapists uh may not have a controlled
substance because they're not
prescribing or they might be uh
psychologists without it, but they could
still say that you have PTSD, for
example. That would be within their
scope and could refer. So, just throwing
out some options along this spectrum
between complete in-person controlled
substance versus no all self-certify. I
think uh there could be a happy medium
in there.
Thank you, Kenan. And just as a note, we
are at 11 o'clock. And so what I am
hearing is that um you would like us all
to bring that on back. Um we shall
indeed and look at um other
possibilities with regard to it.
>> Perfect. And then just to summarize um
and board members correct me if I'm
wrong, we are going to send the
practicum hours to the education and
training committee. We extended the
reciprocity deadline. Um and then
what's the final action on the
certifying clinician?
So Ian will take that back um to um here
in the department to reconsider.
>> Perfect. All righty. And then is
everyone still good for the meeting on
the 17th?
Well, and I I wanted to check in on that
as well if if we did in fact want to
switch the times for um the board
meeting at which is currently scheduled
at 9 on the 17th with the um training
and education which is currently at one.
>> Yeah, Johnny, I would recommend we just
leave them as they are because people
have already scheduled
>> unless the board disagrees.
I'm not seeing disagreement. So,
okay.
All righty. And then if the department
is able to stay for public comment, that
would be great. Um, if any of the board
members need to leave, I completely
understand. Um, but thank you all for
being here. I will go ahead and move on
to public comment.
So, if there are individuals who would
like to uh who would like to speak as
far as from the public, um all you need
to do is raise your hand and we will
call on individuals in order. Just as a
reminder, you do have three minutes to
speak during public comment. Um, and uh,
we'll go ahead and start going through
the list.
Okay. And so I see Kate Hawk, you have
your hand raised.
And let me make sure you're you're
sorry, I'm trying to switch screens. Oh,
there you go. Perfect. You got it before
I did, Kate. Thank you. Go ahead.
>> Yeah. Thank you. And I am just going to
quickly say what I put in the chat and
say thank you to everyone who's spoken
up and acted in with integrity. This is
a tough situation and uh I'm glad you're
giving yourself some time to, you know,
take a little more time that'll save us
in the long run. So, um yeah, that's
pretty much it. I mean, this is just
been a couple of rough weeks and I know
it has been for some other people, too.
So, uh appreciate that the you know,
we're moving ahead together and I need
to get on another call. Thanks so much.
>> Thank you, Kate. And it looks like next
we have Elizabeth. Uh, England Kennedy,
um, your mic is enabled. You can go on
ahead and speak.
>> I'd like to thank I'm sorry there's an
echo. I haven't used Teams in a long,
long time. Um, I'd like like to thank
everybody. You've obviously put in a lot
of time and effort and careful
consideration on all of these issues. I
am a little puzzled because Ian is
talking still about a hard deadline on
December 31. Should that exist, I
recommend going back to the legislature
and giving the explanation of we need
costbenefit analysis. Uh we're still
discussing what specific terms mean.
We're still looking at um what
reciprocity means and how we're going to
go through that. There are serious
concerns about access and e and equity
particularly in rural areas. And I'm
thinking of Lee County right now and the
difficulties there. I don't see
inclusion of uh community health workers
and roles they might play or education
they might get. Same with extension
agents. Um I'm wondering whether the
depo department of higher education
might be a useful consultant as well as
um an and possibly somebody from uh
Oregon as well. I will write up
something and send that, I'm assuming,
to Ian and Dominic that's got more
detail and then you can disseminate as
you see best. And thank you for staying
past 11 to to hear our concerns as well.
>> Dominic, you're muted.
>> Thank you, Johnny. Thank you, Elizabeth.
Um I do appreciate that. Um any public
comment um sent afterwards should be
sent to the medical psilocybin email and
I will actually put that in the chat um
so that you have that information.
>> Dominic
>> and I'm sorry I already see Jorge has
already put it into the chat as well as
Ian. So everybody was on that. So thank
you everybody and thank you Elizabeth
again.
Okay. And next up we have Denali. Um
>> good morning everybody. I'm um just want
to thank the advisory board and
department um for the continued
transparency and commitment to to public
participation in this rule making
process. I do really appreciate it. Um
and like Kate want to acknowledge that
the past few weeks have felt um felt
tense and that that tension is
difficult. Um
so much of the transformative potential
of psychedelics med psychedelic
medicines is about um an increased
capacity to move through difficulty and
I remain really confident um that this
is a hard thing that we will move
through together and I think this
meeting um just made that feel even
stronger. I want to say that, you know,
criticism of specific policy choices is
offered not um in an adversarial spirit,
but um offered because we have a shared
commitment to building the healthiest,
most accessible program that we can. Um
and because that shared commitment
carries with it a responsibility to name
design barriers honestly when we see
them. And so I'm just really grateful
that the board is taking some time to
consider this further.
That's all for now and looking forward
to discussing in committee.
>> Thank you, Denali. Uh, next is Trina
Zer. Um, Trina, your mic is enabled, so
you should be able to unmute it and go
ahead.
>> Everyone, good morning. Can you hear me?
>> Yes, we can. Thank you.
>> So, uh, thank you for for the meeting
and it was good to hear some of the
concerns that were presented. um that I
share about the what I perceive as low
didactic hours and some um fierce
concerns about the way that the
practicums are set up by the the current
legislation having to practice with
actual patients. And so I won't uh harp
on those concerns. Um but I wanted to
add a couple of additional details that
may be uh important for us to think
about and that's about the question of
the payment for services when trainees
are involved and transparency about um
them being involved and uh the the
status or permission [clears throat] to
have observers um
in like social work uh practicums,
right? There are some that are unpaid.
There are plenty that are unpaid, but
there are also practicums that do have
an a a payment for that internship. And
when I think about trainees being
involved with actual patients, if the
trainees are paying an educator to
provide those practicum hours and you
have patients also potentially paying
for services, it makes me wonder if the
patients are going to um be paying the
same full payment as uh as another or
whether by having a trainee involved in
their care if that is going to be a a
lower cost. um service.
Uh if if not, um is the educator taking
in all of those fees paid or is there
something that will be allowed per the
the regulation so that there can be paid
internships potentially um not when
someone is simply in an observer role,
but when they are um being observed.
That seems to me as a way to prevent
people from uh systems from being
predatory and wanting to have as many
trainees as possible. Um and making
additional money from that and it also
makes it just more cost-effective for
people who genuinely want to be trained.
But giving all those free hours um can
be a real burden to their their life and
their families. And then the additional
piece um I I would love to see that
patients are given the opportunity um to
opt out of being observed um that
there's full transparency about what
that plan is. Having been in rooms
practicum rooms where there were a lot
of observers in the room that shifts the
dynam the dynamic it really changes the
the the openness and the healing that is
possible. And I think it's important
that we be intentional with that. Um,
and I think that it's important that we
figure out like what a a sensible limit
could be to the number of trainees being
allowed to observe in that that same
session. Um, so thank you for for
hearing me out. Wanted to make sure that
these were heard and have a wonderful
day. Thank you for all your hard work.
>> Thank you, Trina.
Do we have any additional comments?
Okay, I do not see any. I will turn it
back to you, Ian.
>> Well, thank you guys all for being here,
for participating in our meeting, for
giving us your public comments, for just
showing up today. It is so much easier
to not go to things than it is to go to
them. So, thank you for being here. Um,
to my fellow board members, I know you
guys are not paid. You are doing this
out of the kindness in your hearts, out
of the appreciation for the state of New
Mexico. So, thank you to all of the
people of the state of New Mexico. Thank
you for showing up to the committee
meetings, for helping us draft these,
for giving us questions that we may not
have considered otherwise. So, I just
appreciate every single one of you from
the bottom of my heart. Thank you again.
I will now go ahead and adjourn this
meeting. We shall meet again at July
17th at 9:00 a.m.
>> And thank you on behalf of the
department. We really appreciate the
feedback and the comments. And thank you
for being here.